Alexandros Efstratiou CV

Profile

Computational social scientist (social psychology and behavioural science) with interests in intergroup processes and decision-making. I apply these concepts to studying misinformation (and general information processing) and polarization online in the interdisciplinary field of computational social science.

Core skills and competencies

- Experimental and survey design
- Frequentist statistics & machine learning for large-scale text analysis
- Behavioural intervention design
- Research methods evaluation
- Expertise in dual-process theories of decision-making & risk perception
- Computational social media analysis

Education

PhD in Cybersecurity

University College London (UCL), London, UK Supervisors: Prof. Emiliano De Cristofaro, Dr Tristan Caulfield

My research looks at intergroup interaction/polarization dynamics and how they affect the spread of misinformation.

Assignments completed: Systematic review on effectiveness of staff training for secure behaviour | Research project on public perception of scientific consensus during COVID-19 | Literature review on factors of misinformation adherence | Essay on economics of privacy

MSc in Behavioural Science (Distinction - 79.2)

Durham University, Durham, UK

Key skills developed: Behavioural intervention design, intervention evaluation, decision-making theory, cognition of information processing

Relevant modules: Behavioural Insights for Public Policy | Advanced Topics in Behavioural Science | Power and Influence | Applied Statistics | Critical Analysis | Dissertation on leadership biases in Equality, Diversity and Inclusion

BSc in Psychology (First Class Honours - 78.85, GPA 4.25)

University of East Anglia, Norwich, UK

Relevant modules: Research Design and Analysis (I & II) | Psychology of the Individual | Social and Developmental Psychology | Cognitive and Biological Psychology | Social Perception and Behaviour | Psychology of Risk | Brains, Minds, and Machines | Research Project on negotiations

Sep 2020 - Present

Sep 2019 - Sep 2020

Sep 2016 - June 2019

Relevant experience

Behavioural science practice intern

Ogilvy UK, London, UK

July 2019

Research intern

June - July 2018

UEA School of Psychology, Norwich, UK

The project focused on dyadic interactions in negotiation settings.

Other experience

Senior ambassador

Sep 2017 - June 2019

UEA Award, Norwich, UK

Delivered workshops and talks on professional development.

Advocacy Assistant

Oct 2017 - June 2019

UEA Students' Union, Norwich, UK

Provided support to postgraduate students.

Second lieutenant

July 2014 - July 2016

Cypriot National Guard

Platoon commander and director of my battalion's Administration office.

Publications

- Efstratiou, A., Blackburn, J., Caulfield, T., Stringhini, G., Zannettou, S., & De Cristofaro, E. (2023). Non-polar opposites: Analyzing the relationship between echo chambers and hostile intergroup interactions on Reddit. *To appear at the 17th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM '23)*.
- Efstratiou, A., & De Cristofaro, E. (2022). Adherence to misinformation on social media through sociocognitive and group-based processes. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW2 2022).*
- *Hughes, J. P., Efstratiou, A., Komer, S., Baxter, L. A., Vasiljevic, M., & Leite, A. C. (2022). The impact of risk perceptions and belief in conspiracy theories on COVID-19 pandemic-related behaviours. *PLOS One, 17*(2), e0263716.

Conference talks

Efstratiou, A., & Marcinko, A. J. (2021). The leader oversight bias in justice and hypocrisy evaluations of organisational diversity practices. *Academy of Management Annual Proceedings*, 2021(1).

^{*}Joint first author.

Service

- Reviewer, CogSci 2023
- Shadow reviewer, S&P 2023
- Secondary reviewer, WWW 2023
- Program Committee member, ICWSM 2023
- Reviewer, CSCW 2023
- Shadow reviewer, NDSS 2023
- Shadow reviewer, IMC 2022
- Shadow reviewer, ICWSM 2022

Teaching

Teaching Assistant (People and Security) UCL, MSc course, London, UK	September 2023 – January 2024
Teaching Assistant (Probability, Statistics, & Modelling) UCL, BSc course, London, UK	September 2023 – January 2024
Teaching Assistant (Evidence for Decision-Making) UCL, MPA course, London, UK	September 2022 - January 2023

Guest Lecture on Sunk Cost Fallacy (Social Cognition)

Durham University, BSc Psychology course, Durham, UK

Delivered guest lecture on executing search strategies

November 2019

November 29th, 2022

Awards & Honors

- Kurt Lewin prize as top performer in the 2019-2020 MSc Behavioural Science cohort at Durham University
- British Psychological Society Prize for Outstanding Undergraduate Degree Performance as top performer of the BSc Psychology cohort at UEA in all three years of study
- UEA School of Psychology prize for best dissertation project